Previously on
Star Trek: Strange New Worlds...
Is everything
all right. Captain?
We're going back out.
Captain Pike.
Lieutenant La'An Noonien.
Chief of Security.
- La'An.
- Hey. Chief.
Wait. you two know each other?
She helped me
find my way back home.
Permission to return
to Enterprise.sir.
- What's the mission?
- Explore.
We seek out new life.
new civilizations.
We boldly go where no one
has gone before.
UNA:
First officer's log.
stardate 1224.3.
The Enterprise has arrived
at Hetemit 9.
the site of an abandoned
Illyrian colony.
Illyrians are
a humanoid species known
for modifying their genes
to enhance their capabilities
and levels of function.
However. because
genetic modification
is forbidden in the Federation.
they have always been outcasts.
Our presence here
is part of a standing mission
to discover
what happened to them.
Unfortunately. research time
on the surface is limited.
as the planet is regularly swept
by ion storms.
One of which
is fast approaching.
It's funny how
genetic modification
still puts everyone on edge.
Even you. it would seem.
I just don't like loose ends.
[thunder crashes]
Damn it.
I wish we had more time.
These shelters are pretty old.
We should get everyone back
- to the Enterprise.
- All right. everyone.
pack up your data and head
to the rendezvous point
for transport.
Spock. this is Pike. Come in.
The storm must be interfering.
I'll go grab him.
No. no. I got him.
You get the rest
of the team back home.
Ensign Lance.
Energize.
Commander. I'm having trouble
getting a lock on your signals.
The ion storm is interfering.
Storm's only getting closer.
Enterprise.
One second. Commander.
Energizing.
[whirring weakly]
Transporter Room to Engineering.
Hemmer. I'm losing them.
Rerouting auxiliary power.
Get ready.
Chief Hemmer to Bridge.
Prepare for temporary engagement
of emergency systems backups.
[indistinct announcement
over P.A.]
Engineering to Transporter.
Try it now.
What the...?
How did you...?
I am a genius. Move quickly.
Copy.
[sighs]
Better not be out of miracles.
Mr. Kyle.
Captain and Mr. Spock
are still on the surface.
Captain. I think
I've managed to uncover
a previously undiscovered cache
of journals
that may be relevant.
- I'm looking forward
to reading them.
- Great.
How about we get
to the rendezvous point
before the storm
overtakes us. so you can?
Pike to Enterprise.
Two to beam up.
- [sighs]
- [sighs] I can't get a lock.
- Pull more power.
- Power's not gonna help.
The ion storm is too strong.
We try to transport them
through that.
who knows when we'll get back?
Number One to Captain Pike.
You and Mr. Spock should find
shelter until the storm passes.
- and quickly.
- Copy. Number One.
PIKE:
Suggestions. Mr. Spock?
Run.
PIKE:
Space.
The final frontier.
These are the voyages
of the starship Enterprise.
Its five-year mission:
to explore strange new worlds...
...to seek out new life
and new civilizations.
to boldly go
where no one has gone before.
♪
[boatswain's whistle sounds]
The captain and Mr. Spock
are stuck on the surface.
As soon as it's safe.
we'll get them back.
In the meantime.
we do our jobs. Cadet Uhura.
can you get a signal?
No. Commander.
The ion storm is functionally
a communications blackout.
I want to know the second
you connect with the captain.
- Yes. Commander.
- Lieutenant Wheeler.
I want round-the-clock
monitoring of the storm.
The second it starts to let up.
I want to know.
And tell Chief Kyle
to have relief ready.
I want the transporter
standing by.
[indistinct announcement
over P.A.]
ORTEGAS:
Ensign Lance?
Are you all right?
It's too dark in here.
Okay. it's been a long day
for all of us.
But maybe this is something
you should. you know.
do in your own quarters?
LANCE:
I need to feel the light
on my skin.
Whatever tweaks your freak. pal.
[grunts]
What the hell are you doing?
Ortegas to Security.
I need help on Deck 14.
Computer.
increase illumination 25%.
[exhales]
Number One to Dr. M'Benga.
What is the status
of the landing party?
M'BENGA:
Good evening. Commander.
Funny you should mention it.
I have several of them
in here as we speak.
presenting with some
very curious symptoms.
I was about to call you.
Are you feeling all right?
- I'm okay.
- Better come down here
and let me check you out.
just in case.
On my way.
M'BENGA:
It's odd.
Half of them have burned
or shocked themselves.
all on sources of illumination.
and yet
the light's the only thing
that seems to calm them down.
[sighs]
They're being attracted
to light.
So much so they're willing
to hurt themselves to get to it.
I take it you haven't exhibited
any of these unusual behaviors?
No.
You found nothing else
in their systems?
No form of contagion?
Well. the transporter's
biofilters
would have screened out
anything abnormal.
But I ran viral and bacterial
scans anyway as a precaution.
They're clean.
Only thing I've been able
to find
is a severe drop
in cholecalciferol.
Vitamin D?
All show levels in the red.
Outside of this
and the aberrant behavior.
you'd never know they were sick.
How were my vitamin D levels?
Normal.
Whatever affected them
seems to have missed you.
I'd like to take a blood sample
nonetheless.
Commander?
Of course.
Have you been able to reach
the captain and Mr. Spock?
Still too much interference
with the storm.
[whirs]
We'll have to hope
they weren't exposed
to whatever this is.
I have to believe the landing
party came into contact
with something down there
that the biofilters missed.
HEMMER:
Nonsense.
The biofilters would have caught
any contamination
during transport.
Unless it was something they
weren't programmed to catch.
Can't happen.
If they don't recognize it.
they filter it out.
What about the ion storm? Could
that have interfered with it?
- No.
- [beeping]
I mean...
...it shouldn't have.
And yet M'Benga's got four
landing party members
in sickbay.
Anything else abnormal during
transport you can think of?
Besides the landing party's
atoms
almost getting mixed up into
a puddle of bioorganic stew?
No.
I can sense that expression.
you know.
Oh. I know.
You had to pull a lot of power
to keep pattern stabilization.
Could that have inhibited
the biofilters?
Not only are all
the ship's transporters
networked for emergency power
distribution.
the new systems have discrete
backups for biofilters
and pattern stabilizers.
I will run a level 5 diagnostic
ship-wide.
- To make you feel better.
Commander.
- Thank you.
Which. I might add.
may well take all night.
[indistinct announcement
over P.A.]
[boatswain's whistle sounds]
UNA:
On screen.
Number One?
Are you and Lieutenant Spock
all right?
We're fine. but the storm has
us pinned down in the library.
We have an emerging situation
here.
Landing party members
are getting ill.
The doctor thinks
they were exposed
to something on the surface.
[distorted]:
What kind of something?
Apologies.
The signal's out again.
The storm's interference
is too strong.
UNA:
Computer. show me everything
you have
on Illyrian
genetic modifications.
specifically related
to disease control.
COMPUTER:
Working.
Computer.
isolate any files pertaining
to the original
Illyrian settlement
on the Vaultera Nebula.
Records are limited.
[sighs]
You wanted to see me. Chief?
Yes. Several landing party
members
are showing symptoms
of some kind of contamination.
Security needs
to keep an eye out
for anyone exhibiting
strange behavior.
Mm-hmm.
Illyrians?
You think this contamination
might be related to them?
I don't know what to think.
I'm just doing research.
Well. it seems to me.
things like this are exactly
why the Federation is so wary
of genetically-modified species
like the Illyrians.
You start breaking down
the genetic code.
who knows what the unexpected
consequences can be?
If the problem originated
with the Illyrians.
maybe they could also
provide us with a cure.
Isn't using any Illyrian
medical tech
against Federation regs?
Thanks to the Eugenics Wars.
I imagine you know all about
that period in history.
Well. you don't grow up with
a bioengineered mass murderer
as your ancestor
and not develop a thick skin.
Khan Noonien Singh.
Made myself a kind of an expert
on him when I was a kid.
I never think of you as a child.
Yeah.
For a while there.
the worst thing
that had ever happened to me
was a bunch of
the other kids' teasing.
I'd hope that someone
with your last name would know
that snap judgments made
on genetics are faulty at best.
Individuals are
so much more than just...
Is it me or is it dark in here?
[exhales]
- UNA: La'An?
- [exhaling]
Is this the only light you have?
Number One to Dr. M'Benga?
M'BENGA:
Commander?
I think we have a new problem.
M'BENGA:
Same vitamin D deficiency.
Same attraction to light.
She wasn't part
of the landing party.
She never went down
to the planet.
I know.
How is that possible?
How is it spreading?
- I don't know.
- Internal contact tracing
shows that Lieutenant Noonien
shared a turbolift
with Ensign Lance.
- It's a possible source
of exposure.
- M'BENGA: Maybe.
Except whatever it is
isn't being passed
by any traceable viral
or bacteriological means.
What do you recommend. Doctor?
To keep it from spreading.
full lockdown.
UNA:
Computer. open a channel
ship-wide.
Attention all crew members.
we are initiating
Level Five lockdown protocol.
effective immediately.
All nonessential personnel
will be confined to quarters
until further notice.
All on-duty personnel
will be confined to specific
work zones until further notice.
You have your orders.
[thunder rumbling]
I believe there is
a human phrase.
"A watched kettle never boils."
It's a pot.
And in this case.
I'm pretty sure
we're gonna get hit
with the scalding water.
You are deliberately mixing
my metaphor
in order to indulge
your anxiety.
There are sick people on my
ship. and we're stuck down here?
I don't like feeling helpless.
Pacing relentlessly
back and forth
will not change the situation.
[thunder crashes]
PIKE:
This place is fun.
They should sell tickets.
It seems this particular group
of Illyrians
wanted to join the Federation.
As Federation law forbids
genetic manipulation.
this group was attempting
to reverse its DNA modifications
to gain entry.
De-engineering themselves.
as it were.
- That's a new one.
- Indeed.
Any clue as to what happened
to the colony?
I am only halfway through
these records. Captain.
Consider maybe skipping
to the end
before the storm tears
the building apart?
[thunder crashes]
[high-pitched shriek]
Tell me you saw that. too.
I did.
Although what I saw.
exactly. I am not sure.
[whooshing nearby]
UHURA:
What are y'all doing?
Computer. end simulation!
- What did you do that for?!
- We need light!
UNA:
How many more?
Almost 50. I had to open
our auxiliary bay
to handle the overflow.
CHAPEL:
Contact tracing
is all over the map.
Some people are getting it
after being down the hall
from someone who's sick.
Meanwhile.
Cadet Uhura's roommates
both came down with it.
she's completely fine.
UNA:
Hemmer. did you find anything?
Of course. That's why
I'm wandering around the ship
in the middle of the night
running diagnostics.
For fun.
Doctor. we need to check your
emergency medical transporter
for systems integration
and excess power usage.
Please!
I have research in there.
[sighs]
You doing anything right now?
If you hadn't noticed.
I'm in the middle
of a ship-wide
medical emergency.
Trust me. I've noticed.
[whirring]
[gasping]
My medical transporter is fine.
That shouldn't have affected
the lights.
Please stop messing around
in here!
You're only making things worse.
Point taken.
Whatever made that sound.
looks like it's gone.
A curious figure of speech.
[warbling]
Captain.
[high-pitched shrieking]
- I think we know
what made that sound.
- Indeed.
Oh. you're lucky.
Any closer and that
could have hit the carotid.
On a human.
The journals did mention
unconfirmed rumors
of creatures
living inside the storms.
I think we can confirm them.
[heavy thudding]
What do you think the odds are
that'll hold?
Perhaps we should weight
probability in our favor.
A lockdown is instituted.
you're off duty. you come here.
Your roommates contract
the contagion. you do not.
Why?
UHURA:
I went to bed.
Like this?
I closed the door.
I need it pitch-black
to fall asleep.
I'm like The Princess and the...
...Pea that way.
Uhura was exposed to the same
conditions as her roommates.
with one exception:
she was in the dark.
I ran an electromagnetic scan
on the ship.
Around infected crew members.
light waves carry
additional energy.
The contagion travels on light.
[chuckles softly]
Insidious.
And remarkable.
The most successful viruses
propagate in a host.
then trigger
a spreading response.
The way a common cold
makes humans sneeze
to transfer itself
to other humans.
Once we're exposed.
this virus triggers
our pleasure centers when we are
in close contact with light.
Light is literally everywhere.
Any light wave could carry
the infection.
CHAPEL:
It's only a matter of time
before we all become infected
if we don't stop it.
So how do we stop it?
What's the one thing
we can control
that counteracts light?
Dark hates light.
light hates dark.
So we turn off the lights.
We have a sickbay
full of patients
who are essentially
light addicts.
The virus is gonna make them
very uncomfortable.
Would it be too intrusive
to sedate all of them?
Given the alternative...
...I think it's the best option.
Computer.
narrow search parameters
to Illyrian
genetic modifications.
- COMPUTER: Classified.
- Override.
Narrow search parameters
to Illyrian
genetic modifications
related to disease control.
- Classified.
- Override. Override.
Alert. Blackout override
in Transporter Room.
Danger of critical
circuit overload.
Commander Chin-Riley
to Transporter Room.
- What's going on?
- [whirring]
Acknowledge.
Computer. clear screen.
[low rumble]
Hemmer. what are you doing?
Performing a miracle.
Come in. You'll enjoy it.
[gasps softly]
What is that thing?
An iron-sulfur alloy. I believe.
It took all my skills to isolate
a portion that could transport
from the core of Hetemit 9.
It's not fully materialized.
You're transporting a piece
of the planet's core?
Mantle. to be precise.
I want to feel the radiance
on my skin.
I've almost stabilized
the signal.
Hemmer. it's a thousand degrees.
It'll kill you.
More like 10.000.
Just a few seconds more
and it'll be here.
[high-pitched whirring]
Hemmer. stop!
♪
[heavy thudding]
[weapon whirs]
Does that thing have
a setting for stun?
I am arming us with knowledge.
You think the Illyrians knew
how to stop these things?
Perhaps.
But even if they did not.
we may be able to learn
from their misfortune.
I have deduced that these
creatures did not destroy them.
That. in fact.
they began to appear
as the Illyrians were starting
to be wiped out
by a mysterious disease.
I'm still waiting
for the useful part.
SPOCK:
I have found no entry describing
the creatures causing harm
to the colonists.
My ears are popping.
The atmospheric pressure
is rising.
Ionization levels in the storm
are now lethal
to organic matter.
[metal creaking]
Ground.
[grunting]
♪
[panting]
- Looks like they're gone.
- Indeed.
And thanks to them.
it would seem. we are not.
How in the exact hell
are you carrying him?
UNA:
Never mind. He needs to be
sedated before he wakes up.
I'm afraid I'm going
to have to be next.
My cholecalciferol levels
are plunging.
And it's down to Nurse Chapel
and myself. I'm afraid.
You took my blood earlier.
Did you find anything that
could help synthesize a cure?
- Just because you haven't
caught this thing yet...
- I'm immune.
- You don't know that.
- I've already come down with it.
and my immune system did what
it was bioengineered to do.
I didn't tell you earlier
because...
...I'm an Illyrian.
- Would that even work?
- No.
Why not? My body knew how
to fight off the infection.
It's not that simple.
There are other factors.
Neither of us has
any experience with...
your unique metabolism.
Mm.
Why do I get the feeling
you're about to quote
Starfleet regulations?
Oh. no. I'm not. I just...
Look. I know there's a directive
against mixing human
and Illyrian blood.
but I couldn't
care less right now.
Then why are we wasting time?
- [groaning in distance]
- Go.
- What is the issue?
- I've looked at your blood.
It has no novel antibodies.
And that is consistent with what
I know of Illyrian biochemistry.
You don't create antibodies
that lie dormant.
Your immune system
literally burns out
new infections immediately.
Which means I have nothing left
to synthesize an antidote from.
So I'm protected
but I can't help anyone else?
Perhaps if I was there
at the moment you were infected.
- You'd better put me out.
- UNA: No. no. no. wait.
We'll come up with something.
- There's nothing
to come up with.
- [exhales]
You're a Starfleet doctor.
There's always something.
You put a lot of faith
in Starfleet.
That must be hard.
Starfleet is right
about a lot of things.
but not all of them.
Not about us.
- If my blood...
- I understand.
Prejudice has kept people from
helping each other for centuries
with no scientific
justification.
And after we met our neighbors
in the galaxy.
we found new bigotries.
Human and Vulcan blood.
Now it's human and Illyrian.
In any case.
they're meaningless to me.
I am a physician.
I'd beg you to help
if you could.
regulations be damned.
But you can't help here.
I'm sorry.
[exhales]
Now put me out.
Before I lose control.
COMPUTER:
Warning. Warp core containment
field has been deactivated.
Recommend reestablishing
containment field immediately.
[alarm sounding]
Warning. Warp core containment
field has been deactivated.
Warp core breach imminent.
La'An.
[alarm sounding]
Warning. Containment field
has been deactivated.
Warp core breach imminent.
UNA:
La'An. stop.
Back away from the panel.
- That's an order.
- Denied. Commander.
You know what'll happen if that
containment field goes down.
We'll be flooded with light.
La'An. stop.
Danger of exposure
to matter/antimatter radiation.
Containment field at 75%.
Seventy percent.
Fifty-five percent.
Radiation nearing
critical levels.
LA'AN:
Let me go.
Containment field at 40%.
Get off of me!
I'm trying to help you.
It's me. La'An.
You know me. I'm your friend.
You lied to me
every day for years.
What kind of friend is that?
- 30%.
- You're an abomination.
An augment.
That's what the other kids
called me
when they heard my name:
augment. monster.
Like you are.
[grunts]
Radiation levels are now toxic
to organic species.
Warp core breach imminent.
[communicator trills]
Pike to Enterprise.
Do you read me?
I think it's safe to go
back out now.
We'll get a stronger signal.
Those plasma creatures...
they went to great lengths
to save our lives.
They shielded us
when the storm broke through.
Why wouldn't they have done
the same for the colonists?
I see two possibilities.
They were not motivated
to save them
because of some previous
interaction with the colonists.
And the second?
They were unable to save
the colonists
because they are the colonists.
How?
I found mention
of some odd behavior
in reaction to the disease
I mentioned earlier.
The infected had a compulsion
for light.
Some were driven so mad.
they ran into the storms.
chasing the lightning.
Wouldn't they have died?
Yes.
Although it is possible
the charged storm particles
bonded with the colonists'
electromagnetic presence.
creating what we saw.
Fascinating.
This is a thorough account
of the colonists' initiative
to renounce
their genetic engineering
in order to join the Federation.
It would seem. even in death.
they wanted us to be aware
of who they really were.
What is it. Spock?
Some Illyrians were.
among other things.
bioengineered to fight disease.
Had they not tried to reverse
their augmentation.
they may not have all died.
They wanted to join
the Federation so badly
their good-faith gesture
got them killed.
[hypospray hisses]
UNA:
It's okay.
It's okay. We got an antidote.
La'An tried to jump
into the warp core
while the containment
field was down.
As I was stopping her.
she got a bad dose of radiation.
and so did I.
Apparently. my body
cured both of us
before I reengaged the field.
La'An is not an Illyrian.
Her proximity to the commander
created chimeric antibodies
in her system.
I was able to synthesize them
into a cure before they set.
Don't thank me.
I know I'm good at my job.
Everyone here owes you
their life.
There's something
I need to take care of.
Mind if I sit?
You pack one hell of a punch.
Lieutenant.
Thank you.
That wasn't a compliment.
What's the penalty for striking
a superior officer?
I can't seem to remember.
Thanks.
I mean. we're friends. right?
Do you want me to tell you it
was just the sickness talking?
I don't know. Was it?
Yes. And also. no.
All my life I've hated augments.
Hated what-what people
thought of me
because I was related to them.
Understanding why they were
outlawed in the Federation.
The damage they did.
They almost destroyed Earth.
The augments. yes. but not us.
My people were never motivated
by domination.
Illyrians seek collaboration
with nature.
By bioengineering our bodies.
we adapt to
naturally-existing habitats.
Instead of terraforming planets.
we modify ourselves.
And there's nothing wrong
with that.
If that's what you believe.
why do you hide it?
Why hide it from me?
I've been hiding it
from a lot of people.
[inhales]
All I ever wanted.
since I first saw the stars.
was to join Starfleet.
I know.
You're the one who gave me
that dream.
And the fact that strawberries
are my comfort food.
[clears throat]
UNA:
Captain.
I'm an Illyrian.
Not from this colony.
from far away.
Starfleet policy is clear.
By not disclosing
my genetic augmentation...
worse. by enlisting
in Starfleet...
I've committed
a Federation offense.
I am resigning my commission
and surrendering myself
for disciplinary review.
I only ask that my sincere
desire to join Starfleet
be taken into consideration.
Rejected.
- Sir?
- I don't care
where you come from.
You're the best
first officer in the fleet.
Thank you. sir. but I feel
obligated to point out
that Starfleet does not allow...
Una. stop.
Chris. that's kind. but I've
broken a dozen regulations.
I lied to get into Starfleet.
According to Federation law.
if you shelter me.
they could come after you. too.
I welcome that discussion.
One thing became clear to me
on Hetemit 9.
Illyrians are severely
misunderstood.
Your actions in the crisis
prove that again.
I just did my job. sir.
No.
You defy every stereotype
the Federation has
about Illyrians.
You're an example to them.
And to all of us.
What do we do
when Starfleet finds out?
[chuckles softly]
You let me worry
about Starfleet.
Oh. before you go...
Uh. the glitch was with the
transporter's biofilter. right?
That's how the virus
got on board?
- Let's get that fixed.
- Yes. sir.
M'BENGA:
Come in.
It was your medical transporter
that inhibited the biofilters.
The new transporters keep
biofilter and pattern integrity
power systems separate.
But you didn't let them upgrade
the medical transporter
when we were in spacedock.
I'm starting to suspect
you couldn't.
Hemmer's diagnostic
shows you're keeping something
in the pattern buffer.
And whatever it is.
you needed to preserve it.
even if it ended up killing
everyone on the ship.
- Isn't that right. Doctor?
- No.
I didn't know.
It was an accident.
What are you keeping in there
that could be worth
all our lives?
Not what.
Who.
Rukiya.
My daughter.
A year ago. she was diagnosed
with cygnokemia.
Brutal disease.
You can't imagine what it's like
to watch your child wither away.
To see a lifetime of potential
reduced to a 12-week prognosis.
I'm sorry.
I am chief medical officer.
On the flagship of Starfleet.
You'd think I'd be able to do
something about it.
But nothing worked.
Did you know there's no limit
on how long you can store
someone's pattern
in the buffer?
You just have to materialize
them regularly.
In the buffer.
my daughter doesn't age.
And her disease can't progress.
We travel light-years in hours.
And somewhere out there
is a planet that has
the discovery I need.
Only...
...the light virus epidemic
was my fault.
It seems so. yes.
If I thought. even for a second.
that could have happened...
It won't happen again.
I can't endanger our crew
for one life.
No matter how much
that life means to me.
But I ask. would you consider.
before you return me
to Starfleet.
that I might have a chance
to spend
a little more time
with my daughter?
To say goodbye.
No.
I'll provide a dedicated
power source.
direct from the warp core.
This problem?
We can ensure
it never happens again.
[door whooshes open]
I look forward to meeting her
one day.
First officer's personal log.
The lights are back on.
But that doesn't mean
we see clearly.
People are always hiding things.
Hi. Dad. Story time?
You bet.
- Now. where were we?
- King Ridley was about to climb
the tower
to rescue Princess Thalia
from evil Queen Neve.
[shushes]
Wait.
[chuckles]:
No spoilers.
Dad. we've read this.
like. a hundred times.
That doesn't mean
that the ending
couldn't miraculously change.
UNA:
Dr. M'Benga stopped
hiding today.
just a little.
And for once.
I did. too.
I told Captain Pike
the truth about myself.
And he defended me.
Told me I was exemplary.
That he would fight for me.
So why do I feel terrible?
What if I hadn't saved
all those lives?
Would the captain feel the same?
What would he do
if I wasn't a hero?
One of the "good ones"?
When will it be enough
to just...
...be an Illyrian?
Computer.
Delete log entry.
COMPUTER:
Log entry deleted.
M'BENGA:
If King Ridley would seek out
the Mercury Stone
and win it as his own.
his victory over Queen Neve
would be assured.
It is said
that in the right hands.
the Mercury Stone has the power
to cleanse the land of evil
and bring prosperity to all.
But if it were to fall
into the wrong hands.
the Mercury Stone's power
would bring about a terrible.
long-lasting dark age
across the land.
Captioning sponsored by
CBS
Captioned by
Media Access Group at WGBH
access.wgbh.org